Hello and welcome back to Python Core and Applied Concept for Reliable Data Sence Workflow.
So in the last video we concluded our discussion of functions and today we will now begin
the discussion of an important data structure in Python which is called Dixnary.
Okay, so let me begin the discussion of Dixnary.
We just like list Dixnary is no other data structure which is very popular in Python
and the closest that you can relate it to is something called structure in C.
Although I mean it's not good to relate data structure into programming languages
and you can never have no one to one kind of correspondence between data structure
depending on different programming language. But if you're coming from a C background
you may find it you know easy to relate it to structures but no let me you know discuss this
from very you know scratch I mean even if you don't know about the structure don't worry.
So Dixnary in Python is a data structure that stores data as key value pair.
Okay now in the list if you remember we could store multiple data entries in the single list
right and the way to access those entries in the list was using indices right one two three
zero one two three. So by default I can access any entry in the list using its corresponding index
so that was a you know a way to access elements in a list but Dixnary provides you a more
explicit you know sometimes very you know helpful way of accessing element while other key
okay so keys are like you know names for those values that you can store in a Dixnary okay
so it is all the advantages of you know list and on top of now you know unlike you know
numerical indices Dixnary use meaningful keys to organize and access data so this is a core
of Dixnary so you have both key and value pair so you can give meaningful name in in in
in in form of keys and for those meaningful names you can actually assign values which
which are called actual values okay so that's why we call key value pair so there may be multiple
key value pair in the you know same Dixnary just like you know list you can have multiple values
you know kept at different indices here you may have multiple values you know kept using or
you know kept using this key values okay so if you want to access later you can use this key value
so let's talk about syntax and semantics of Dixnary by creating through very you know elementary
so to begin with now if you want to let's say create a empty you know so let's learn about
the syntax by using these small examples okay and semantics as well so if you want to let's say
create a empty list in Python so let me call this list empty you know sorry the Dixnary
if I want to you know create an empty Dixnary then no this is the syntax that I normally prefer okay
so you can you know simply start a curly brace and in it and this represents a you know Dixnary
I mean if you write something like this it means that you have created an empty Dixnary and the
name that you have assigned is empty Dix you could have chosen any other name here instead of
no empty Dix but I'm just keeping this name not as an informative you know name so that we can
know what we can alternatively also you know create this you know empty list by calling
for this you know Dixnary constructor so no Python has a Dixnary constructor which let me
create another empty Dixnary Dixnary and let's call it something different no this is an
alternative way of creating a predixnary and you can call this method okay so the semantics of
both these syntax are same either you write this way or you write no this way in both the cases
you are actually creating a no empty Dixnary okay so this this you know constructor dict
actually creates empty Dixnary you know if you pass no values here I mean it will create
some Dixnary with initial values okay so this is the no way to create you know empty Dixnary
in Python for example what if I let's say print
let me print both
empty Dix here what shall I expect when I print this
what you see I expect empty Dixnary because this is what was here
from what if in the other case if I print let me print the
this alternative way of creating empty Dixnary if I have empty Dixnary alternative
than if I again print it you see again you have the same empty list okay so all the I mean
these two look different from the syntax point of view the semantics is same okay so we can
get the same effect of creating empty list what if you want to create a list with some initial value
let's so let me you know create you know sorry create a Dixnary with which contains no information
about students okay so let's call it student Dixnary and then so the way to create
again so if I wanted to empty Dixnary this this is this was not enough but if I want some values
to be stored in this Dixnary from the beginning I can also initialize them the first thing so
you're normally when we know right key we use strings as key values okay so that's most
no convenient and no natural way to use no key values so here what I say is I
not write down my first key is the name of this student okay this indicates that now I'm talking
about the name of this student and let's say I have one student in my class
heartic okay so heartics it also be my string because this is the name
and if I talk about the age so let's know put some again I mean the age can be here the key
can be the strings so key can be in a more general thing key can be any you know immutable
no data types but here I mean we are using simple strings to refer to some meaningful you know
values which we want to hit by these keys okay so the age actually represents the age and let's
call the age is not 20 and then let me put some also great corresponding to this is student
so the way to do this is we create another key which is called great and we assign some value
corresponding to this key let's assign the grade A and finally let me have the courses that
this student has taken already okay courses maybe another key that this student has taken and then
in the courses I may have no multiple courses so no more convenient ways I mean I create a
list which stores all the courses that he has let's take it so in this case let me say that he
is taking math course and he has also taken some science courses okay so this is how we can
actually create a no list which is not empty okay so this is student list okay which has
interest of one of the student I mean no okay so let me know what happens if I print this
okay to see whether this has been created properly or not we can just print this
and see what happens so when I print this dictionary that we created just now you can see
all these you know key value pair appear right so the name is hard the age is 20 great this one
and courses that he has taken is this one okay so remember in this case no you have
in the courses here you have a mutable data types right this is the list itself so the value
is mutable so later on if you want you can actually add some more courses to this list okay so this
is how we can initialize our dictionary with some initial values sheet of no always initializing
as a empty again I mean using our dict constructed you could do the same thing I mean let's say
I mean instead of this if I want to now define the teacher one of the teacher of the class then
using the alternate method so I what I call is I call this no dict constructed and then
is it up you know just empty of parenthesis what I put it is all the value that you want to
initialize this dictionary with so you have no key value pair okay so the way to assign this key
value pair here is you name you know give the name of the key and then assign the value okay so
here I mean what you can do is you can give it you know the name of the teacher is and is
it up no code and we use this kind of you know we assign our name to be let's say
be shake and subject that I teach maybe maths okay
and then my years of experience one can know from this data structure
it's five and that's it because this is again an alternate way of creating it so I by default follow
the first one I mean if I want to initialize but this is again another way by which you can
create a dictionary okay and now what if I print it so can we just check the semantics also
or by printing it whether it has created a dictionary that we intended to create it okay so
and you see you you get the no same no similar kind of dictionary right with key value pair
no although I mean not one thing I mean I have not given this key as a string right I have just
no written the string without putting it them in code and by default what it takes is this
string them as a string okay so this is the you know internal working of Python Python
texture of that so you don't need to actually put them in you know this partition so you can
simply write the name of the key and then assign the values okay so this is difference in syntax
but as you see the semantics is more or less same I mean you get the same thing okay so good so
now we know how to create you know different you know simple dictionaries inside Python programming
language now as I mentioned I mean the keys can be various you know different immutable data types
also right so so it may not make sense right now but in some circumstances this might come
as handy okay so let me know first know or I don't what do I want to say so in the place of key
you you need not always write down no strings like this yes also string like name age or this
kind of thing so you can also use any immutable data type that you can not come up with so that's
possible for example you know if I want to create a simple example let me call it mixed let's say
you know call it mixed keys example okay and in this mixed key what I do is I create an open
dictionary you know very first thing I keep as no simple string key let's say you know
follow string key okay this is normal not type that we have been discussing so far here you keep
in any any value let's call it a value one we keep here
the second when when you're initializing this kind of dictionary for the second key I can
I know you simply one two three so this is also no perfectly valid okay so we need not always
give no string to the left hand side of this colon so in key value I can simply write it down this
no one two three which is no integer and since integer are also you know immutable data types
you can actually write it there and you can write anything here let's say you know call value
that we write here this no call value do okay similarly what are the other you know I'm not a
type that you can think of which are no immutable so what about tuples we can also write don't
tuple on the left hand side of this colon okay so I mean this may look no weird right now
you may not find it no useful but no in some cases you may find it to be useful for example let's
say if I want to know I'm working with some geometry right and I want to store the coordinates like
X and Y coordinate of a point you know in in the plane or no in in euclidean space in that case you
can actually write this in X Y G or X Y kind of thing on the left hand side and on the right hand
side you can actually write on the exact value of those no X Y coordinate instead of not creating
these X no Y and G separate keys right so so that may be useful in some cases so but no I leave
it to you to think about what can be you know good use cases for this kind of you know more
general immutable types which can appear on as key on the left hand side okay for example here
I mean for simplicity to show you that this syntax is perfectly valid I you know created some
no arbitrary key which I called you know 1 comma 2 which is a tuple right this is a tuple
and I assign some value to it and let's say what are the some other I mean can we also write down
this you know Boolean kind of immutable data types towards as a key this is also perfectly valid
okay so if you write down now I have some value let's say for value 4 okay so so this is no
perfectly allowed I mean if I now want to compile this what will happen let us try to
compile this and see so there is no error right so by the accepted all of this that we have
written just now so value can also be any data type you know just like you know
just as a way we have created keys as different data types value can also be you know different
data type and here there is no restriction that the values that you keep in the dictionary has to
be immutable they can be even you know mutable okay for example let me let me you know now creator
another dictionary which has so instead of mixed key we have now mixed type of let's say values
in this dictionary okay so we again want to create a dictionary let me create a dictionary
but there are multiple or key value pair the very first key value pair is let's say the name itself
okay so name that the name is you know some name maybe
and what about the again we can repeat the same thing right from here you take all these things
great and this the courses I mean we have already seen no one such thing right where
the courses was let me copy this right so in this case you can see you know in the
value field you have string here here you have no integer here again you have a string
but here you have a you know mutable that type right and this is list you cannot write this
on the left hand side of a dictionary I mean on the left hand side of the colon as a key okay so
you cannot create a key which is a list okay so no this is the difference that I wanted to
to mention here you can also have no dictionary right because dictionary is also
mutable that type you can simply write down a dictionary which let's say I mean in this case
if you want to give some extra information about this student you can maybe say now these are
some extra information that I want to pass okay info and what is the info key what what does it
contain so it contains a dictionary where you may want to talk about the city okay you may want
to talk about the city right let's say you know call it either way and then you can now talk
about the zip code right I mean you can create a meaningful dictionary to you know store useful
information something like this okay so this is no perfectly no valid thing to do in
python okay so okay so so so this is what I wanted to mention that now the difference that you
should note here is this kind of data types the list data types and the dictionary data type which
come on the right hand side of colon when you know define a dictionary but they're not allowed
on the left hand side okay so what if I know so that is some error so maybe I forward some comma
somewhere let me just after this we have to separate all this key value pair with comma so hopefully
if I compile this now this is no word okay so now we know how to create no no dictionary right
simple dictionary you know into dictionary as well as how to do what are different types of
key that you can create okay so in the case you can have actually these tuples okay and there's
no boolean values which are immutable but you cannot have no list or dictionary in the key value
but least and dictionary can appear as a value inside the dictionary okay this is all we
wanted to know now the next question is that no one's you know define some data structure you
also want to access the element of the data station like for for example in the dictionary if I
want to access some value of the dictionary corresponding to a key how to know go about doing
that okay so the simple way is to use this you know bracket notation okay this is grand bracket
this and so again I mean let me you know bring a dictionary quickly for you
let me so let's assume that we have you know this dictionary
now again a student with name age you know this major minor information and then
grade point and I want to actually as the name of the student okay in this case you know it's
Bob right so how to access it now access means I want to access it and store it somewhere let's say
okay so what we are going to do is we want to see how to
access values using key okay so the first thing is I want to know maybe
we have the student name and store it in a student name no variable so how to do that so this is
no exact syntax how we can do it so we write the dictionary name which is no student and then
we pass you know inside this bracket this key value for which we want to know on the exact value okay
so the name of the key you have to pass inside this bracket so first you know name the dictionary
and then in the square bracket you have to pass the key for which you want to know the value
so for example in this case I want to know the name of the student so student followed by name
and that will return us Bob and the Bob will be stored in student name okay so what about
now the age so if you want to know the age of the student so in this case now it's 22 so again
maybe no copy this thing I'm
bested here and then change the student name to maybe student age so what shall I write
here instead of the name key I want to now access the age key and age key has this
22 so now if our understanding of the semantics is correct then if I print this student name and
student age what shall I get here is the name Bob and the age 22 okay this is how you know we
expect this to know so let me you know print it so what if I print now let's say
in the very first case no what I'm trying to do is I'm trying to print the name okay
and where did I store the name in the student name
no very good and if my way of accessing the values in the dictionary is correct then this should
return me the no correct name that I have accessed so what about you know age we can have no
same you can print it let's print the same thing with this being now age instead of name and
a variable that where we store this age is this variable and if you print it so what do we
first shall we expect do you see so this is the semantics that we expected and this is correct
so our method of accessing no different now values corresponding to key the dictionary is correct
now what will happen I mean let's say I mean there should we know I mean this square bracket
helps us and I access different no value for corresponding to different keys in the dictionary
but what if I pass some key which is not there inside the dictionary is for example in this case
let's say I've not stored the full number of this student here but what if I you know want to
access the full number the student doing the same in a method so shall we try it so what I'm
saying is let me not try to access something which is not present in the what I'm trying to do
here is now I'm accessing
full number which is not already there in the dictionary so let let's no try to compile this and
see what happens I mean do we get something and inform so when we compile it I mean
the no Python actually tells us that this is not there right so the key there there is a key error
that happened there why because no full number is not there so so it will throw you this no error
measures okay so this will not okay so there is an error right when you compile and try to run
this code so if you have not defined something and if you want to access now this way that will be a
problem okay so you know this is what we wanted to see here and now assuming let's say now we have
not we are not accessing something which we have not defined now what if we want to maybe you know
access so now just as we discuss in the case of list we have to be a little careful with
you know multiple values in the dictionary also now if you if your dictionary has you know some
of the values or values corresponding to some keys are multiple then you know while accessing you
have to be a little careful I mean whether you want to actually access it just for as a copy or you
want to you know access it and change the value so since multiple you know data types can be
changed later on so you have to be very careful about your intention of accessing those
no key so do you want to change those key or you just want to access it read it and then use it in
some other computation and don't want to change the actual dictionary okay so this would be very
clear in your mind so so your quick example let me again you know bring up so what we are
trying to emphasize here is we want to talk about working with mutable values in the dictionary okay
so in this case let me know bring again the same similar
okay so so let's say we have a student on dictionary where there's a second key value pair has
value as a mutable data type right here we have a list now you can actually access this list
using the way we say right so this is about the age right so this list corresponding the age
information okay so what if I want to know access this age in student age so let's say call it
student age and then how to access this list so we can just name the key value and pass it here
and the effect will be that we so this no student age here refers to another mutable list that is
there inside this don't explain what will happen let's say if I now try to modify this student
variable and since the student age variable has a list I can actually access the elements of
list right using this variable and let's say I want to change the value at the position one
and let's just want to set it zero now since no student age has a list inside it certainly I'm in
this variable or this list you know value at the index one will change so what was this student
is initially having 22 24 and 26 right so it was position one so position one was this position
because no list start with zero so if I set that position one value to zero certainly I mean I
can expect that in the student age variable that I have created right now this should change but
will it change in the original student dictionary so this is what we are trying to discuss right now
it turns out that this will be a change here as well you know in the original dictionary
why because this was no mutable data type and when you assign this actually you know you assign
this variable reference to the same list that is there in the dictionary data structure
okay it's not that I mean you have passed a complete copy of this list to this student age
so this assignment simply you know gives a new name a student age to the same you know object
that is there in memory which this age is also referring to okay this is very important to keep
in mind and you know the way to see here is that if you now you know print this you will see
what will happen to the student that structure that we created so let me print
what student and then see what happens to do you see the change here okay so this is what we
wanted to highlight with this example that you know so now what we want to discuss is if there is
a error let's say using the normal method of access which tries to access some key and if the
key does not exist then in the previous case we saw that there were the error measures right like
this so in this case if you remember I mean we tried to access this for number and for number
was not there already in the dictionary data structure so it was an error so a safe way to
no access element without getting this you know error message is to use the get method in Python
corresponding to every dictionary okay so for instance I mean what we are saying here is that
this kind of get method that we are going to discuss right now is a safe way of
not returning values of dictionary keys if the not dictionary key does not exist right
in any that case it will not return us a non-value okay so this get method
returns non if key does not exist that's not exist
does not exist okay so can we have a quick check of this so let me know bring the exact no code
for this and then see you so the way to have a safe access is this one so every say phone
now is equal to student.get and then phone number we pass as a key value even if the phone number
is not there something will be written and that value should be none in this case is what
now we are claiming so if you print this what what do we expect here so can we just run this
be support and see maybe get a none right so the get with the fall value also can be used okay so
if you don't want none value to be now thrown then alternative is you provide to this
not get method the default value that you want to you know get stored into the variable which
is trying to access this key value okay so again I mean to be more precise if I don't want this
none value to be now passed and then say if I want to pass some other value in this case
let me bring the code here so if I so this is an alternate way of using the get method so you pass
on the key value if the value is not available you may want to you know return some meaningful
information like you know not provided instead of you know none okay so so you can pass
any other information you want here which you think is you know meaningful and then if you
again print in this case you will see what's the value pass the value pass this you know not provided
so these are some no ways of accessing the keys in a safe in python if the keys value are not
they're already okay now that we have seen how to create dictionary and access
its entries we want to know about how to update and modify dictionary so how to for example add
new key value pair to any dictionary that is already existing okay so again let me now bring
quickly dictionary first dictionary here let's call you know this dictionary to be
student dictionary which has these three fields and what we want to do is we want to add now
new key value pair okay for example for this you know student I may want to add this
minor major information and the GPA so how to do that so the way to do this is
have just kind of a statement okay so the important thing to note here is so this is the how we
remember you we accessed also the value corresponding to key right so adding the dictionary name followed
by the no key where you want to assign the value you use this no square bracket to access
now that thing and then you can use the simple assignment operation that we have studied and
here you can know put this as well as you so remember that this is not there okay so the major key
is not there but this will not give you an error why because you are not accessing this element
what it the semantics the internal semantics of Python say that if this key is not let's say
available already then you create this key and then add this value okay and that's why I mean
this will not throw you an error message unlike the previous case where no when we use the square
bracket to access some key which was not already there you got the error message okay in both
this case as you will not get the error message and if you want to know print now let's say
your student placed
okay and this point what will we get now you see we started with it all in name and age right
but now it also has these other key values that we added that run here okay this is how you
can not add things you can also modify existing thing in a plane where I mean and you can guess maybe
how how to do that for the same let's say my student that we are talking about we can update
the existing value by now using something as similar that we have done with list also
okay so what about if I want to change the age to 21 now nine set of 20 and then
no GPA to 3.8 so I can simply I know use this kind of syntax and assign values and it will be
changed okay so just to see whether what we did make sense and is accepted by Python we can print
here and then see for the result you see I mean the age has been now updated to 21 and the
GPA has been updated to 3.8 and this is the simple syntax to do this okay now instead of you know
doing know these update 1 by 1 what you can do is you can now also have multiple update okay
no update no by that so instead of you know doing all these update 1 by 1 what we can say is
we can call this update method and do it in one go okay so we can update multiple values
at once so for example what just not to be concrete no let's take another example and so you so
what I'm saying is we can use some syntax like this where I am just saying dictionary.update
which is no what is the dictionary in them student and then update and you know in this no parenthesis
inside this parenthesis you again open this dictionary you know curly notation and then say that
age I want to update to 22 I also want to you know maybe add you know in the update you don't only
want to maybe modify things no because no for modifying we know we may also want to add some new
no key value pairs so that also you can simply say here in this way and the graduation
unexpected graduation here is this way so what it will do is it will you know update the existing
with the current value and if the keys are not already there then it will create this new key
and you know update your dictionary accordingly okay so this is the you know syntax so remember
to call this update method on this dictionary student and this is how not to know the exact
semantics I mean we can just print and see what happened to our
student if you know like I said remember we we mentioned what is the major but we did not
mention what is the minor you know there's a graduation here and if I do this update now can I
see those reflected in the original dictionary so let me run it and now you see you you have all
those information right you you have stood as minor as well as the graduation year as additional
field so we can also you know do update on nested dictionary but there you have to be a little
careful you know some and you may you know encounter some not very hard to identify you know bugs
if you are not careful so we can have you know dictionaries inside dictionaries also okay and in
that case if you want to let's say modify the you know inner dictionary then you have to be a
little careful you cannot do with no simply by no the way we are doing here for example again to
make it more concrete let me know bring a dictionary which has a dictionary inside it
so in this case our dictionary is again a student dictionary but not previous one where we have name
as at least but then the grades in the grade no key we the value itself is a dictionary okay so
this is why we call it a nested dictionary okay so dictionary has another outer dictionary has a
key whose value itself is a dictionary remember this is a dictionary so in the grade I am willing to
let's say or I want to store units for different subject that he has taken like maths and science
and these are the values other you know grades that he obtained in this no subject so this is let's
say our current dictionary which is a nested dictionary and if I want to now upgrade the grade let's
say if I want to know upgrade the grade and maybe you know include one more no subject maybe
right I mean he has taken let's say English now and you want to add this to the previous one okay so
what if we call the update method that we use just now let me ask you what will happen if I
do something like this okay so what I'm saying is you know in the grades no go to the student
or student dictionary and update and in the grade field I want to say that I add this one
so what will be the effect of this one I mean more do you guess I mean will this
English be added here in this existing one or something else will happen
okay so can we print and see I mean what happens if I do something like this if I open now
student what is your guess what will happen you see in the grade I mean we only have now English
grade right because this is how we say that you update the student dictionary so you have
called this update on the student dictionary and then said that update the grades as this one so
what it does it assigns this dictionary as the grade and it loses the initial to values that you
had in the beginning okay so if your intention is just to add this one thing then you don't call
the update on the student dictionary okay so you have to call this update method somewhere else
right and what is the correct no place where you should try to you know add this so
so in this case since we lost it so let me again maybe you know create the same
dictionary here just repeating it because we lost try it when we updated we lost this math and
science so now we again have let's say math and science and now we want to upgrade this dictionary
and not the outer dictionary so now the correct syntax to do this should be to first access that
key and then call update method on that okay so please think about it
completely carefully and try to convince yourself that this is what we should do if we want to
really upgrade this grade and add one more you know English language here okay up to this point
so what shall we do we shall first access it no student grades and so when we say student grades
so what does this mean so this itself is accessing you know now this dictionary
and what we are saying is now we want to update we want to call update on this dictionary instead
of the outer dictionary so when you do this update and then you add this to no new key value pair
you will see that your old values are not replaced okay so can we now print and see again
what happens to this one
now you see we did not erase the previous you know values in the dictionary the
inner dictionary but we know append its some values which are these values right so this is
now all about updating values in a similar way you can also
any move values from the dictionary I guess this is not quite possible to remove existing value
from dictionary and the way to do that is to know use this no pop method which we also
discussing in the case of I think list right so for instance if I have let's say a dictionary
which is like this one we have grades of all these things and if I want to know let's remove some
specific value pair from this grade okay so let's say I want to know pop the history thing from
here okay so or remove the history value so what I can do is I can write a syntax like this
that you from the grade you pop the history and whatever it is remaining you keep in the
remote grade and then if you print the remote grade what you will see is
can we now see the
more removed one and what is in the remote one and then what is in the remaining one so
the remaining one should be in the original grade right so let me
print without this to see what happens if I print this you see in the remove
one which is which we stored here we got this no 78 which is the history grade and the remaining
one which means the original grade now does not have key value pair corresponding to history
okay so this is how you can actually not remove entries from no key value pair from your dictionary
if you want to clear everything from you know that dictionary you can actually say that no
dictionary got clear okay so this will clear everything for example in this particular case if I
want to completely flush out everything from this no grades dictionary so what I say is I
will call this grades dot clear method and this will actually it is everything from this
dictionary and after that if you want to print again or maybe print these grades
so can we see what happened so the grade is empty now you can completely get rid of this whole
dictionary by saying that now you delete the entire you know no grade thing and okay so so here
what I said is now we flushed out everything from the dictionary so dictionary is empty but I can
also say that no you delete the dictionary completely
for example this action and then you print it said
grades what what shall we expect we see we we expect a name error because there is nothing
called grade now after we have done this action okay so this is all about you know removing items
from a dictionary now let's discuss some very common dictionary method and operation that we use
most of the time when we are working with dictionary so okay so so the very first kind of
no thing that we want to do is no access all the keys or you know values of dictionary or even
all the items of the dictionary you know what about what is the way to you know list all of them
or access all of them okay so for instance I mean let me again give you a concrete example what
we are praying to say here is if we have let's say our dictionary like this
and we want to get all the keys in the dictionary let's say okay so how to access all the keys
in the dictionary so we are only interested about no keys and not the values let's say so the
now ways you call this dictionary dot key method okay so very quick way of accessing all the
keys of the dictionary that we are talking about maybe use this syntax so if we print
inventory so in this case no inventory was our dictionary so inventory dot keys
now this will return all the keys and I'm just now casting it to list so that now I can print
clear now so you okay so if I do this then you can see and when we run this we see all the
keys in this one okay similarly we can also no print only the values and no no access all the
values of in the dictionary and not their key so a syntax which allows us to do this
is very similar to this one except the value part okay so we use the same things here I
prefer to remember we use inventory which is our dictionary dot value so this dot value method
we'll get us the values which is stored here and I again no cost it to list
for no better printing so what shall we expect here 10 5 and 8 is what we can expect
so this is how we can access all the values okay so the semantics is exactly what we can expect here
now what about if you want to you know get this pair itself and let's store it in some list
okay as tuple maybe okay so if I want to no get this no key value pair as tuple and then
no maybe store it in some list so what I can do is I can say no give me that using dictionary dot
items so there is no three method that we are using here for us first one is dictionary dot key
which gives you only key then dictionary dot values which gives you not only values and then
the dictionary dot item gives you both this key value pair as tuple okay so what I'm telling you
right now is that what if I want to store all this key value pair in a list so then I can
you call I can use syntax which is not like this so dictionary dot item so this items will return
all these no key value pairs tuples inside the list okay and let me just see what happens
you see I mean these are the tuples that you get and you can use the same you know length
function to you know get the length of you know dictionary to to say I mean how many you know
keys are there in this no dictionary okay this is also no possible so you can use the same
thing that we use in the case of list now you can iterate so since we can access these keys
and values now you know we can also iterate over them so there's no very much possible okay
because we could access them so we can actually iterate over them and do some actions which we
want to you know refer to where we want to refer to these keys or values okay so like it's just
like I mean it rating over loops you wanted to iterate over different elements of loop and do
something according to what you could access or where you are present in the case of dictionary also
we can iterate over no different key value no pairs in the dictionary and do something that we
want to do with those no key value pair okay so we can iterate through keys okay so so we can
iterate through key value pair and we can iterate through values also so all of this is no possible
so for example again I mean let me bring quickly dictionary which contains the student scores here
let's say this is the dictionary which no contains the student score here and if I want to iterate
through keys let's say now first we know we want to iterate through keys so what we can
and what are the keys remember they're a student name right so what we can say is
we can use the syntax like this so for student in student scores
okay so by by default when you know write down no for student in student score so this student
takes the value of keys okay so you don't need to explicitly write no dot key so you can simply write
no for a student in student scores so the dictionary name and by default it takes no iterate over
key values okay so what is there in the student for each of these you know iteration these value that
is present here as key the student names okay and if you print what is there in this what you
expect is all this student so the iteration will cause printing of these key values is what we
are expecting here so let me print it and so you so you see I mean when we print it what we get
in a student here is not the by default this key values okay but if you want to you know iterate
over no different no items of this thing and maybe you know not now and print these no student
as well as there is score so we can actually do this no key value iteration also okay so for that
again we can use something similar as we have seen do recall I mean our previous discussion of items
here if you remember this item actually returns key value pair so we can use something like that
to get both the values now if you want okay for example in this case what we can do is if you
want to print score for different let's say student then we can use this syntax
for a student in for a student know how much score in student scores dot item you see students
score dot item contain tuples right key value pairs and list of key value pairs so now you are
saying that take the key to be student and no score to be put in this score and then you print
both no student and score okay so this is how you can access both the field information or whatever
is important for you using this kind of syntax okay so let me now run this to see what happens
and you see we could print all these things right so this is how you know we can you you can
actually iterate over the items instead of it trading over only the you know keys or it's
trading over the values okay so good so now we know how to iterate over keys iterate over values
and how to iterate over you know items so I don't think I have discussed how to iterate over
no values right so to iterate over values again actually you can use you know dictionary dot no
value I think we have already we have listed it right this is what we discussed there so no need
to discuss it again so if you want to use you can use actually for loop and do I trace it to do some
meaningful let's say computation by trading over values also the way we did for this to think
okay so with this we would like to no conclude our discussion of dictionary with a few observations
for dictionaries are better than list certainly in some cases when you want to look up information
by meaningful keys right for example you know the same student data you could have created using
you know three different list and by default you might have no assume that every index correspond
to the same entry for example you know Alice has age 20 and grade 85 okay and simple little
this kind of thing but then the method of accessing information regarding every student may not be
that simple I mean you can do in principle but then you know go through this code to figure
out that no this is not that simple okay and this is not explicit way of doing it you have to always
keep in mind you have to get the indices of Bob to know what was his no age and what was his grades okay
so of you know although it's possible to do everything know with list but it's not that convenient
and that's why we have this dictionary that the structure here things are more explicit and
hence efficient in this case you can see for Alice all the information I could keep at one place
and if I want to access I can simply say that no for Bob give me the grade so you can just say
you know students go to Bob and then get that grade so it is very easy to access and effort to
know values in a dictionary because it's organized in a very nice way and it's a very structured
way of representing things right I mean you not only give the values but you also give the name
that those values correspond to so that's why I mean these are self-documenting nature dictionary
where you have no meaningful keys to represent what values they correspond to and it may be very
convenient in most of the programming exercises and we will do some of them in the programming classes
and you'll see dictionaries are very very useful in now implementing those kind of programming
our computational tasks okay so with this I would like to conclude to this lecture I will
meet you in the next video till then goodbye